Finding Aid for the Albert Boime Papers LSC.1834
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 3: Research materials, 1941-2008
  - Black Imagery, 1982-1999
    - Puerto Rico, 1982-1983 (Box 97, Folder 2)
      Notes, drafts of "Oller and the Image of Black People in the 19th Century" and "Oller and the 19th Century Puerto Rican Nationalism." Folder also contains 4x5 transparencies.
    - Slavery, 1986-1989 (Box 97, Folder 3)
      Photos, notes, photocopies, 4x5 negatives, bibliography, and publishing agreement.
    - Slavery, undated (Box 97, Folder 4)
      Format letter for image requests for "Art in an Age of Bonapartism", bibliography on slavery and African Americans in art, photocopies of artworks, and symposium concert program for "On the Eve of the French Revolution Literature and Politics in the Age of Goethe."
    - The enslaved and free, undated (Box 97, Folder 5)
      Notes and bibliography.
    - Jacobs - slave trade, 1999 (Box 97, Folder 6)
      Correspondence with Nancy (Editha) Jacobs regarding outline for paper "Art as a Weapon: The Use of the Visual Arts with Special Reference to Cartoon and Caricature, in the Campaign to Abolish the British Slave Trade and Slavery, 1780-1834."
    - Art of darkness, undated (Box 97, Folder 7)
      Notes and paper by Boime titled "Art of Darkness."
    - African Americans, 1988-1989 (Box 97, Folder 8)
    - History, ca. 1992 (Box 97, Folder 9)
      Photocopies, notes, lecture, and student paper.
    - Thomas Noble - images of black people, ca. 1988 (Box 97, Folder 10)
      Notes and draft of article "Burgoo and Bourgeois: Thomas Noble's Images of Black People."
    - Hierarchy and subordination, undated (Box 97, Folder 11)
      Notes, photos, and pages from unidentified draft.
    - Art of exclusion, undated (Box 97, Folder 12)
      Photocopies from Boime's book Art of Exclusion, draft of a preface, and pages from manuscript on William Sidney Mount (likely for lecture "Racism and Minstrelsy").
    - Permissions - hierarchy, 1988-1991 (Box 97, Folder 13)
      Correspondence and draft of insert for Art of Exclusion.
  - Arshile Gorky and Armenian Genocide, 1996-2005
    A significant portion of materials in this subseries were compiled or represent the work of Boime's student Ramela Grigorian. The subseries is arranged by topic.
    - Gorky, 2001 (Box 98, Folder 1)
      Photocopies and thesis preparatory work by Ramela Grigorian.
    - Gorky and the Armenian genocide, 2003, 2005 (Box 98, Folder 2)
      Articles and conference abstracts regarding the Armenian genocide. Folder also includes draft of "Chapter I: The Armenian Genocide and Arshile Gorky."
    - Armenia - Gorky, 1996-1998 (Box 98, Folder 3)
      Outlines, stories of genocide survivors compiled by Ramela Grigorian, photocopies, slides, correspondence, and paper "The Armenian Genocide and the Unpaid Life Insurance Policies" by Hrayr Karagueuzian.
    - Armenia, 2003 (Box 98, Folder 4)
      Notes, photocopies, and Armenia brochure.
    - Armenian, bulk 1997-1998, 2001 (Box 98, Folder 5)
      Paper on Khatchkar, photocopies, outlines, bibliographies, papers and drafts by Ramela Grigorian, and correspondence.
    - Ramela Grigorian, 2001 (Box 98, Folder 6)
      MA Thesis and other degree/department materials for Ramela Grigorian.
    - Miscellaneous Karagueuzian, 1990 (Box 98, Folder 7)
      Notes, correspondence, slides, copy of paper "A Concise History of Fountain Pens," and investigation paper "Ventricular Fibrillation as Chaos" by Hrayr Karagueuzian.
  - The Holocaust, 1993-2004
    Materials correspond to Boime's research on the Holocaust, including a particular interest in revisionist scholars and Holocaust deniers. The subseries is filed by topic.
    - Holocaust monument, undated (Box 100, Folder 1)
      Draft pages from "The Architecture of Aftermath" by Terry Smith.
    - Entartete kunst, ca. 1991 (Box 100, Folder 2)
      Photocopies, notes, clippings, and catalog for "Degenerate Art" exhibition at LACMA.
    - Der sturmer, undated (Box 100, Folder 3)
      Draft of chapter "Der Sturmer and the Stormtroopers", photocopies, and notes. Some materials in German.
    - German socialism, undated (Box 100, Folder 4)
    - Der ewige Jude pictorial, ca. 1994 (Box 100, Folder 5)
      Notes, draft of chapter "Der Sturmer and the Stormtroopers", and clippings.
    - Other genocides, 1999, 2002 (Box 100, Folder 6)
      Clippings on global genocide issues such as those in Kosovo, Cambodia (including catalog of exhibition on Cambodian art), and Armenia.
    - Holocaust, 1993-1998, 2000-2004 (Box 99, Folder 1)
      Notes, e-mail correspondence, and dissertation proposal by Andrea Liss "Trespassing through Shadows: History, Mourning, and Photography in Contemporary Representations of Holocaust Memory." Some materials in German.
    - Holocaust notes, 1995-1999 (Box 99, Folder 2)
      Clippings, photocopies of "Der Ewige Jude" [The Eternal Jew], exhibition materials for "Exiles and émigrés: The Flight of European Artists from Hitler" at LACMA, notes, and promotional materials regarding opening of Museum of Tolerance in Los Angeles.
    - Goldhagen reviews, 1996-1997 (Box 99, Folder 3)
      Clippings and photocopies of reviews of Daniel [Erich] Goldhagen's book on the Holocaust: "Hitler's Willing Executioners." Some materials in German.
    - Holocaust revision, bulk 1999-2000, 1990 (Box 99, Folder 4)
      Clippings regarding the trial of a Holocaust revisionist and other Holocaust deniers. Folder also includes printouts of email correspondence.
    - Klemperer, 2000 (Box 99, Folder 5)
      Photocopies of "I Will Bear Witness: A Diary of the Nazi Years, 1939-1941" by Victor Klemperer (some underlining and notes, presumably by Boime).
    - Nazi society, 1997-2001 (Box 99, Folder 6)
      Clippings, e-mail correspondence, and internet articles regarding controversial Holocaust publications, draft of "Chapter 1: Art in the Third Reich and its Link to Volk and Religion" by Sandra Esslinger.
  - World Wars, 1981-2003
    Boime's research on war and art, with a particular emphasis on World War I and II. The subseries is filed by topic.
    - World War I, 1981 (Box 100, Folder 7)
      Notes, correspondence, and booklets on Kandinsky, war images, Max Beckmann, and Cuban and Mexican murals. Some materials in German.
    - World War I miscellaneous, 1991 (Box 100, Folder 8)
      Photocopies, correspondence, and clippings.
    - World War II art pillaging in Europe, 1994 (Box 100, Folder 9)
      Correspondence.
    - World War II miscellaneous, 1994-1995, 2002 (Box 100, Folder 10)
      Student paper "Varian Fry and the Emergency Rescue Committee: The History and a Critique," clippings, and student paper "Painting War: The Intersection of Global Conflict and Modernism."
    - Film, 2003 (Box 100, Folder 11)
      E-mail correspondence.
    - Hiroshima, 1994, 2001 (Box 100, Folder 12)
    - War and art (1 of 2), 1983-1987, 1999 (Box 100, Folder 13)
      Dissertation proposal "The Emergency Rescue Committee and its Artist-Clients in Vichy France and the United States, 1940-1942," notes, correspondence, and copy of lecture "Making Art at the Front: Cubism and the First World War in France" by Elizabeth Kahn Baldewicz, exhibition brochures on Kandinsky.
    - War and art (2 of 2), 1983-1987, 1999 (Box 100, Folder 14)
      Dissertation proposal "The Emergency Rescue Committee and its Artist-Clients in Vichy France and the United States, 1940-1942," notes, correspondence, and copy of lecture "Making Art at the Front: Cubism and the First World War in France" by Elizabeth Kahn Baldewicz,
    - Heartfield, 2000 (Box 101, Folder 1)
      Photocopies, correspondence, notes, student paper "The Propaganda of the First World War and its Influence on the Photomontage of the Berlin Dada Movement," catalog of works by John Heartfield, and paper "The Art of Engagement" by Wayne Andersen. Some materials in German.
    - Enola Gay, 1995 (Box 101, Folder 2)
      Brochures, flyers, notes, and materials from Historians' Committee for Open Debate on Hiroshima. Other materials also include clippings and correspondence regarding a teach-in.
    - Civil War, undated (Box 101, Folder 3)
  - Censorship, 1989-1996
    Boime's research on censorship, particularly as it relates to art and visual material. A significant portion of this subseries is concerned with instances of censorship by the NEA. The subseries is arranged by topic.
    - Censorship, 1990 (Box 101, Folder 4)
      Correspondence, syllabus and course materials for Art History 253: Corporate Art, Government Protection and Free Market Obscenity, and paper by Suzanne Loizeaux-Witte "Bordering on the Obscene: Censorship, Aesthetics, and Morality in the American Body Politic, 1980-1991."
    - Censorship symposia, 1992 (Box 101, Folder 5)
      Conference materials for UCLA symposia on censorship in the arts, and notes. Other materials include articles and photocopies regarding artistic freedom.
    - Censorship, 1991 (Box 101, Folder 6)
      Class rosters, syllabi for Art History 127 course on censorship, and clippings.
    - Censorship, ca. 1994 (Box 101, Folder 7)
      Articles and clippings.
    - Censorship, ca. 1996 (Box 101, Folder 8)
      Museum News magazine and research materials.
    - Censorship seminar, 1989, 1994 (Box 101, Folder 9)
      Press release, photocopies, articles, and AVISO newsletters.
    - Art History 253, Winter 1990, ca. 1990 (Box 101, Folder 10)
      Art History 125 syllabus and bibliography, photocopies, articles (from Museum News, ArtNews, and Corporate Art Report), and clippings and photocopies of articles regarding Robert Mapplethorpe and censorship.
    - NEA, 1990 (Box 102, Folder 1)
      Photocopied articles, notes, and student papers on NEA funding for New York Theatre and the Robert Mapplethorpe censorship controversy.
    - Art and politics, 1990 (Box 102, Folder 2)
      Paper "Art and Politics" by Carol A. Wells of the Center for the Study of Political Graphics with lengthy edits and commentary from Boime.
    - Political correctness, undated (Box 102, Folder 3)
      Proposal at College Art Association conference for panel on art history and political correctness.
    - NEA and censorship, 1989 (Box 143, Folder 9)
      Correspondence (including letters between Nora H. Brougher and several senators), articles and letters regarding NEA grant decisions and censorship, and packet of materials from the Coalition for Freedom of Expression.
    - Pornography, 1990 (Box 143, Folder 10)
      Notes, project description for post-doctoral studies by Clare Spark, annotated photocopies from "The Politics of Propaganda," and mid-term examination questions for summer course Art History 150D on "Obscenity and Art"
    - Mapplethorpe article, 1989 (Box 147, Folder 6)
      Photocopied article from LA Weekly about Robert Mapplethorpe.
  - Business of Art, 1972-2003
    Materials relating to Boime's research on the business of art. General topics of interest include artists as entrepreneurs, the art market, patronage, and research on other industries. The subseries is filed by topic.
    - Artist as entrepreneur, 1975, 1979 (Box 102, Folder 4)
      Notes, correspondence, photocopies, and illustration lists. Some materials in French.
    - Collectors, undated (Box 102, Folder 5)
    - Man-Max, 1972 (Box 102, Folder 6)
      Correspondence, notes, and annotated photocopies.
    - General and basic, 1973, 1975 (Box 102, Folder 7)
    - Footnote additions, undated (Box 102, Folder 8)
      Annotated footnotes relating to Freud.
    - Basic core, undated (Box 102, Folder 9)
      Notes (topics include European Economic Development).
    - Publishers, undated (Box 102, Folder 10)
    - Bankers, undated (Box 102, Folder 11)
    - Department stores, undated (Box 102, Folder 12)
    - Literature, undated (Box 102, Folder 13)
      Notes (Topics include Flaubert and Zola) and draft of "Entrepreneurial Patronage in Nineteenth-Century France."
    - Sugar, textiles, undated (Box 102, Folder 14)
      Notes (catalogues) and photocopies.
    - Steel and sundry, undated (Box 102, Folder 15)
    - Definition, undated (Box 102, Folder 16)
    - Rothschilds, 1973 (Box 102, Folder 17)
    - Dealers, 1973 (Box 102, Folder 18)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 102, Folder 19)
      Clippings from Princeton publication and "Guns, Globalization, Greed: A Guide to the New World Economy" edited by Christopher Ney and circulated by War Resisters League.
    - Art theft, ca. 1998 (Box 102, Folder 20)
      Magazine and newspaper clippings and photocopies regarding art thefts.
    - Patronage - contemporary, 1978 (Box 102, Folder 21)
      Clipping from LA Times Home Magazine regarding an art collecting couple.
    - Lewis, undated (Box 102, Folder 22)
      Notes on Wyndham Lewis.
    - Camera work, ca. 2000 (Box 102, Folder 23)
      Notes and galley proofs of several artworks (in color).
    - Dealers now, ca. 1991 (Box 103, Folder 1)
      Promotional brochure for Jill Newhouse (a gallery or auction house).
    - Art market, 2002-2003 (Box 103, Folder 2)
      Christie's education catalog and exhibition brochure on business of art.
    - Avant-garde, ca. 1986, 2001 (Box 103, Folder 3)
      Copy of paper "The Avant-Garde Object: Form & Fetish between World War I and WWII" by Jack Spector, article "The New Adventures of the Avant-Garde in America" by Serge Guilbaut, annotated photocopy about Clement Greenberg's theory of art, and Hammer Museum exhibition brochure for works by Paul Pfeiffer.
    - Photo IDs, 1988-1989 (Box 103, Folder 4)
      Correspondence, 1 slide, and images and 4x5 transparencies of artworks (majority portraits).
    - Print techniques, 1991 (Box 103, Folder 5)
      Exhibition brochure for "The Re-Design of Nature: Graphic Constructions of Natural Space in Europe, 1760- 1860" by the Grunwald Center for the Graphic Arts, UCLA.
    - Business of art (1 of 2), 1987-1988 (Box 103, Folder 6)
      Clippings, correspondence, draft of paper "Bonaparte's Subsidy of the Art of Engraving: A Decree and a Note on the Musee Francais/Royal" by George D. McKee, slide request forms, notes, images of works by Simon Dinnerstein, interview notes (unclear who interviewee is), and photocopies on topics like Yoruba art.
    - Business of art (2 of 2), 1987-1988 (Box 103, Folder 7)
    - Entrepreneurs, 1988-1989 (Box 103, Folder 8)
      Notes, correspondence, and draft of "Rethinking Patronage" (later to be called "Entrepreneurial Patronage"), 4x5 transparency, and copies of images.
  - American Art, 1986-2003
    - The Getty, 1997-1998 (Box 103, Folder 9)
      Clippings regarding the Getty Villa and correspondence.
    - Return to LA, 1998 (Box 103, Folder 10)
      Clippings, photocopies of articles, exhibition proposals and announcements, and booklet regarding artwork in Our Lady of Angels Cathedral (Los Angeles).
    - San Diego, undated (Box 103, Folder 11)
      Photocopies of articles regarding San Diego art.
    - Regionalism, 1987 (Box 103, Folder 12)
    - American impressionism, 1986-1987, 1997 (Box 103, Folder 13)
      Photocopies of articles and clippings.
    - Urban realism USA volume V, 2000 (Box 103, Folder 14)
      Clippings and paper "American Expressionism" by Bram Dijkstra
    - Historical scholarship, 1988 (Box 103, Folder 15)
      Clippings, articles, and paper by Barbara Ann Day "Representing Aging and Death in French Culture." Some materials in German.
    - Art in America, 1977 (Box 103, Folder 16)
      Correspondence from editor of Art in America, notes, and business cards.
    - Exhibition packet, 1989 (Box 103, Folder 17)
      Exhibition Packet for "Paris 1889: American Artists at the Universal Exposition" at the Chrysler Museum.
    - Primitive, undated (Box 104, Folder 1)
      Notes, photocopies, correspondence, annotated photocopies, and paper on "The Metaphysics of Baseball" by Roland Garrett.
    - Auction, 1987 (Box 104, Folder 2)
      Notes and Auction and Exhibition Catalogue from The Knoedler Library.
    - Notes, undated (Box 104, Folder 3)
    - Photocopies, undated (Box 104, Folder 4)
      Photocopies from one of Boime's volumes on Couture and notes.
    - Students, 1989, 1997 (Box 104, Folder 5)
      Art History Department Meeting agenda, description of LA Department of Cultural Affairs Percent-for-art program, and booklet from graduate student symposium "Images and Spaces of Transformation: Festival, Spectacle, and Ritual in Visual Culture."
    - California Impressionism, 1998-1999, 2003 (Box 104, Folder 6)
      Notes and various exhibition brochures.
    - California Orientalism, 2003 (Box 104, Folder 7)
      E-mail correspondence, notes, and copy of "California Orientalism."
    - California plein air painting, 2003 (Box 104, Folder 8)
      Notes and correspondence related to California plein air, early modernist, and impressionist paintings.
    - 1930s/WPA, undated (Box 104, Folder 9)
      Photocopies (artists of interest include John Graham, Arshile Gorky, and Ben Shahn), dissertation proposal, symposium notes/outline, student papers, and clippings.
    - American art bibliography, undated (Box 104, Folder 10)
      Bibliography for course reserves.
  - Museums, Bulk 1992-2003, 1979-2005
    Most folders contain research on specific museums. Arranged topically.
    - Realist revolt/Whitney, 1995 (Box 104, Folder 11)
      Copy of Whitney Protest Update and petition against Whitney Museum of Art to include contemporary realist painting, drawing, and sculpture.
    - Whitney biennial, 2000 (Box 104, Folder 12)
      Informational packet regarding artists and exhibitions in 2000 Whitney Biennial. Folder also includes correspondence with Museum of Modern Art regarding image requests.
    - Smithsonian PAEC, 1992, 1998 (Box 104, Folder 13)
      Professional Appraisal and Evaluation Committee (PAEC) Report and guidelines. Other materials include call slips, notes, and photocopies.
    - Smithsonian, bulk 1988-1991, 1996-1997 (Box 104, Folder 14)
      Correspondence, photocopies, newsletters, and booklet on Intern Opportunities with the National Museum of American History 1996-1997.
    - Wallraf-Richartz Museum, 1989 (Box 104, Folder 15)
      Correspondence and documentation regarding images from the Wallraf-Richartz Museum. Some materials in German.
    - National Museum of American Art, 1989 (Box 104, Folder 16)
      National Museum of American Art exhibition funding information, photocopies, correspondence, exhibition proposals, and notes.
    - Bellagio Gallery of Fine Art, 1998 (Box 104, Folder 17)
      Photocopied articles and list of works owned by Bellagio Gallery in Las Vegas.
    - Craft and folk art, 1993, 2001 (Box 104, Folder 18)
      Internship and background information from the Craft and Folk Art Museum, clippings and photographs of The Clothesline Project at UCLA, and exhibition brochures.
    - Georgia Museum of Art, 1990, 1998 (Box 104, Folder 19)
      Correspondence with Georgia Museum of Art and copy of Georgia Museum of Art News. Other materials include a flyer and note regarding lecture by Judith Wilson (originally referred to as Askman by Boime).
    - Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, 2003 (Box 104, Folder 20)
      Promotional packet for prospective students to Hewitt Cooper New Design Museum.
    - Dahesh Museum, 1998 (Box 105, Folder 1)
      Exhibition packet for "Training an Artist: Alexandre Cabanel and The Academic Process in 19th Century France."
    - Musee Campana, undated (Box 105, Folder 2)
    - Museum studies, 1990 (Box 105, Folder 3)
      Articles, museum newsletters, and press releases. Some materials in French.
    - Museum brochures, 1979-2005 (Box 105, Folder 4)
      Museum brochures (institutions include National Building Museum, Bowers Museum, Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, Guggenheim, Hammer Museum, Museum of Jewish Heritage, Seattle Art Museum, Getty Museum, LACMA, and Huntington Library). Other materials include list of publications of the Wallace Collection and photocopied article "The Getty Scandal."
    - Museum, 1996 (Box 105, Folder 5)
      Copy of Museum News magazine.
    - Museum addresses, 1985-1986 (Box 105, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and invoices from museums regarding photo permissions.
    - Addresses, 1997 (Box 105, Folder 7)
      Assorted correspondence, fax cover sheets, envelopes, and other documents with addresses of publishers, museums, and literary correspondents.
    - Madrid seminar, 2000 (Box 105, Folder 8)
      Fax containing informational materials on ESTER seminar "Language, History and Art in Nationalistic Movements, 19th and 20th Centuries."
    - Roberson, 2003 (Box 105, Folder 9)
      Roberson Museum contract for an exhibition essay.
    - Goupil - Nouveau, 1996 (Box 144, Folder 1)
      Promotional packet from Musee Goupil, likely an exhibition packet. All materials in French
    - Museums, ca. 1996, 1997 (Box 144, Folder 2)
      Calendars and season information for The Getty Museum and the Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles.
  - Late 20th Century Art, 1988-2003
    Boime's research on trends, artists, and movements in art during the second half of the 20th century. Filed by topic.
    - Performance, 1998 (Box 105, Folder 10)
      Description of performance art by Linda J. Albertano and brochure for exhibition "Out of Actions: Between Performance and the Object, 1949-1979" at the Geffen Contemporary.
    - Video art, 1994, 1997 (Box 105, Folder 11)
      Photocopied articles, student papers and bibliographies, and Guggenheim and Getty brochures advertising Bill Viola exhibits.
    - Film, 1996-1997 (Box 105, Folder 12)
      Notes and description of films "Imago" by Meret Oppenheim, paper "The Tactile Eye: Theory and Method" by Jennifer M. Barker, and calendar of activities at California Museum of Photography.
    - Installations - Wilson, ca. 1993, 1997 (Box 105, Folder 13)
      Photocopied articles on installations by Fred Wilson.
    - Andy Warhol, 1989-1990 (Box 105, Folder 14)
      Clippings about Andy Warhol and his work.
    - Art education, undated (Box 105, Folder 15)
      Photocopied article.
    - Bios, 2003 (Box 105, Folder 16)
      E-mail correspondence with Andrew Brainerd regarding obituary for John Rewald (nee Gustav).
    - Gender and Art History, 1993 (Box 105, Folder 17)
      Exhibition brochure for "Daughters of Eve: Representations of Women in Renaissance Prints" at Grunwald Center for the Graphic Arts and article "Critical Critics and Historical Critiques" by Griselda Pollock.
    - Judy Chicago (1 of 2), 1988-1992 (Box 105, Folder 18)
      Correspondence with Judy Chicago (Artistic Director of Through the Flower) and informational materials/newsletters about the organization's Holocaust Project. Other materials include clippings about Judy Chicago, student papers and correspondence regarding Judy Chicago's work "The Dinner Party", articles, and bibliography for "The Dinner Party."
    - Judy Chicago (2 of 2), 1988-1992 (Box 106, Folder 1)
    - Advertising, 1995 (Box 106, Folder 2)
      Student papers on advertising and censorship, brochure for new UCLA student housing and conference facilities, and promotional publication by the Chrysler Corporation.
    - Art and AIDS, 1986-1992 (Box 106, Folder 3)
      Clippings of articles and advertisements and student paper by Wendy Lau "Herstory as Told by Him."
    - Watts Towers, undated (Box 106, Folder 4)
      Notes and photocopied articles regarding Simon Rodia and the Watts Towers.
    - LA culture, ca. 1992, 2000 (Box 106, Folder 5)
      Photocopied articles and op-ed pieces mostly related to LA Rebellion. Folder also includes exhibition brochures on California and masks.
    - Outsider art, 1992 (Box 106, Folder 6)